<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: projects | pfigue]]></title>
  <link href="http://pfigue.github.io/blog/categories/projects/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pfigue.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-04T13:22:47+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://pfigue.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[pfigue]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hypnollama: Checking for 401 Unauthorized]]></title>
    <link href="http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2013/08/10/hypnollama-checking-for-401-unauthorized/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-10T23:59:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2013/08/10/hypnollama-checking-for-401-unauthorized</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some of the services that a webserver provides may be restricted to some specific people.</p>

<p>There are two immediate ways to do this from the webserver level:</p>

<ul>
<li> Use <em>Auth Digest</em> which is not very safe, unless it is provided under an SSL channel.</li>
<li> Restrict by IP address.</li>
</ul>


<p>If the webserver configuration opted for <strong>Auth Digest</strong>, we will get an <strong>401 Unauthorized</strong> answer whenever we try to access the ressource without the adequate credentials.</p>

<p>For this reason, I needed a test to be sure that some services are kept only for a few chosen eyes.</p>

<pre><code>Unauthorized(url='http://..../')
</code></pre>

<p>is the test which does the trick.</p>

<p>If it gets a <strong>401 HTTP response</strong>, everything if fine. Test passes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hypnollama: New test to check for content]]></title>
    <link href="http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2013/08/10/hypnollama-new-test-to-check-for-content/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-10T23:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2013/08/10/hypnollama-new-test-to-check-for-content</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I have programmed a new check for Hypnollama.</p>

<p>This one <strong>checks if the retrieved content after accessing an URL matches exactly what we are expecting</strong>.</p>

<p>I had one similar last week, and the difference is that this new one <strong>follows</strong> redirects, while the previous didn&rsquo;t.</p>

<p>Probably I can have used with <em>httplib</em> as I was doing in the past, but it was easier to use <em>urllib2</em> and actually I discovered how I can prevent <em>urllib2</em> to follow redirects when I want (i.e. in most of the tests). So I am moving all tests to <em>urllib2</em></p>

<p>The name for the test is <strong>CheckContent</strong> and can be used like this:</p>

<pre><code>CheckContent(
        url='http://www.twitter.com/robots.txt',
        expected_content=\
'''User-agent: *
Disallow: /
''')
</code></pre>

<p>I think it doesn&rsquo;t need explanations.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
