<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vagrant | pfigue]]></title>
  <link href="http://pfigue.github.io/blog/categories/vagrant/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://pfigue.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-25T17:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://pfigue.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[pfigue]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Vagrant with LXC Linux Containers]]></title>
    <link href="http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2014/01/25/using-vagrant-with-lxc-linux-containers/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-25T15:44:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2014/01/25/using-vagrant-with-lxc-linux-containers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Containers</h2>

<p>LXC Containers are a relatively new way of virtualization for Linux environments. Solaris had containers since several years ago, but in Linux they appeared around 5 years ago, afaik.</p>

<p>The point of virtualizing using containers instead of virtual machines is that, both, guest and host, use the same instance of the kernel, which translates in <strong>far less time to boot and far less resources used</strong>.</p>

<p>A container is just a set of resources and processes running in a different namespace, eventually with some limitations (CPU or I/O usage, memory used, etc.).</p>

<p>Afair, there are/were 2 implementations of containers for linux: OpenVZ and LXC. Without being an expert in the area, I&rsquo;d say that LXC has much better maintenance nowadays than OpenVZ.</p>

<h2>LXC Containers in Ubuntu</h2>

<p>In Ubuntu 12.04 we can install LXC as usual with <code>sudo apt-get install lxc</code>. As root, we can list the containers we have in every state with <code>sudo lxc-list</code>.</p>

<p>Usually, <a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/lts/serverguide/lxc.html#lxcbr0">once <strong>lxc</strong> is installed, we should find a new network bridge</a>: <em>lxcbr0</em>. You can check if it is present with:</p>

<pre><code>$ ifconfig lxcbr0 2&gt; /dev/null 1&gt;&amp;2  &amp;&amp; echo 'lxc interface is present' || echo 'no lxc interface'
lxc interface is present
$
</code></pre>

<p>Before start to use containers with Vagrant, we should <a href="https://github.com/fgrehm/vagrant-lxc/wiki/Avoiding-%27sudo%27-passwords">work around a bug in sudo (Ubuntu 12.04)</a>.</p>

<p>With <code>sudo visudo</code> you can add the line:</p>

<pre><code>Defaults        !tty_tickets
</code></pre>

<p>to the sudoers file. It will solve the bug.</p>

<h2>Vagrant with the LXC provider</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s create a new vagrant project:</p>

<pre><code>$ mkdir vagrant-lxc
$ cd vagrant-lxc/
$ vagrant init test-lxc http://dl.dropbox.com/u/13510779/lxc-precise-amd64-2013-07-12.box
</code></pre>

<p>Where the URL is an <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/13510779/lxc-precise-amd64-2013-07-12.box">Ubuntu 12.04 amd64 box <strong>for LXC</strong></a> from <a href="http://vagrantbox.es/">vagrantbox.es</a>.</p>

<p>You can use the same <a href="http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-steps-with-vagrant/">Vagrantfile I used in the previous article</a>, but notice that the <code>config.vm.network</code> parameter is ignored by this provider.
At the moment you can only forward port, but not bridge any interface.</p>

<p>Now you can <a href="https://github.com/fgrehm/vagrant-lxc/blob/master/README.md">install there the <strong>vagrant-lxc</strong> plugin</a> with <code>vagrant plugin install vagrant-lxc</code>.</p>

<p>Once done you should already be able to fire up that box with LXC:</p>

<pre><code>$ vagrant up --provider=lxc
[default] Warning! The LXC provider doesn't support any of the Vagrant public / private
network configurations (ex: `config.vm.network :private_network, ip: "some-ip"`).
They will be silently ignored.
</code></pre>

<p><code>vagrant ssh</code> from the same <code>vagrant-lxc/</code> directory to check it, or <code>sudo lxc-list</code> or <code>lxc-ps --lxc</code> to visualice the running containers.</p>

<h2>Advantages</h2>

<p>The time needed to boot up a Vagrant box with LXC is really much lower than using VirtualBox. This translates in faster try-error loop, faster feedback and <a href="http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-steps-with-vagrant/">faster development of Puppet Manifest, server configuration</a>, <a href="http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-steps-with-vagrant/">faster testing of packages</a>, etc.</p>

<p>References:</p>

<ul>
<li> <a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/lts/serverguide/lxc.html#lxcbr0">LXC &ndash; lxcbr0</a></li>
<li> <a href="https://github.com/fgrehm/vagrant-lxc/blob/master/README.md">README for vagrant-lxc plugin</a></li>
<li> <a href="https://github.com/fgrehm/vagrant-lxc/wiki/Avoiding-%27sudo%27-passwords">vagrant-lxc &ndash; BUG &ndash; Avoiding &lsquo;sudo&rsquo; passwords</a></li>
<li> <a href="http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-steps-with-vagrant/">My first steps with Vagrant</a></li>
<li> <a href="http://fabiorehm.com/blog/2013/04/28/lxc-provider-for-vagrant/">LXC provider for Vagrant</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My first steps with Vagrant]]></title>
    <link href="http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-steps-with-vagrant/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-25T12:52:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://pfigue.github.io/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-steps-with-vagrant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Why Vagrant?</h2>

<p>Lately I was developing my-own-solution &trade; for package deployment and now I&rsquo;d to check if I can install system packages without problems.</p>

<p><strong>Vagrant is a tool that lets me create, destroy and recreate Virtual Machines very easily</strong>, so I can in less than 5 minutes, create a new VM with a fresh install of Ubuntu 12.04 and install there the package I want to test.</p>

<p>It can also be useful to test system configuration (e.g. Puppet manifests or Chef recipes, nginx config., etc.) without playing with the production environment.</p>

<p>Another interesting use (and the reason I want to add Vagrant to the development toolchain my team uses at work) is to provide every developer with the option of packing his/her branch and deploy it with the help of Vagrant into a fresh VM, locally on his/her laptop.</p>

<p>Once deployed there, unit and functional test could be run in/against that VM, to be sure that every single branch sent to staging passed a minimal set of requirements.</p>

<h2>Replacing the old-Ubuntu-12.04 Vagrant install with a factory Vagrant.</h2>

<p>Long time ago I installed <strong>vagrant</strong> via <code>sudo apt-get install vagrant</code>, and since then I was getting an error whenever I tried to start a new project:</p>

<pre><code>$ vagrant init test1 http://cloud-images.ubuntu.com/vagrant/precise/current/precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-vagrant-disk1.box
/home/pablo/.rvm/rubies/ruby-2.0.0-p353/lib/ruby/site_ruby/2.0.0/rubygems/core_ext/kernel_require.rb:55:in `require': cannot load such file -- log4r (LoadError)
        from /home/pablo/.rvm/rubies/ruby-2.0.0-p353/lib/ruby/site_ruby/2.0.0/rubygems/core_ext/kernel_require.rb:55:in `require'
        from /usr/bin/vagrant:2:in `&lt;main&gt;'
</code></pre>

<p>I decided to remove the version of Vagrant shipped with Ubuntu 12.04, and install a new one from <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com/downloads.html">the debian package I could get via HashiCorp</a>:</p>

<pre><code>$ sudo apt-get remove --purge vagrant
$ wget "https://dl.bintray.com/mitchellh/vagrant/vagrant_1.4.3_x86_64.deb"
$ sudo dpkg -i vagrant_1.4.3_x86_64.deb
</code></pre>

<p>Due to the first installation of Vagrant, probably all the dependencies were already satisfied and I didn&rsquo;t have to install anything else.</p>

<h2>First project</h2>

<p>In Vagrant, you create a new directory for every project. In that directory will live a <code>Vagrantfile</code> with all the configuration of the VM(s) for that project.</p>

<pre><code>$ mkdir vagrant
$ cd vagrant/
$ vagrant init test1 http://cloud-images.ubuntu.com/vagrant/precise/current/precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-vagrant-disk1.box
A `Vagrantfile` has been placed in this directory. You are now
ready to `vagrant up` your first virtual environment! Please read
the comments in the Vagrantfile as well as documentation on
`vagrantup.com` for more information on using Vagrant.
</code></pre>

<p>If you are going to use Vagrant as a testing/deployment solution at work, you may find interesting to track the Vagrantfile via a <em>git</em> repository.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s edit the Vagrantfile a little bit to redirect the port 8080 on my laptop to the port 8000 in the test1 VM. The result would look like:</p>

<pre><code># Vagrantfile API/syntax version. Don't touch unless you know what you're doing!
VAGRANTFILE_API_VERSION = "2"

Vagrant.configure(VAGRANTFILE_API_VERSION) do |config|
  config.vm.box = "test1"
  config.vm.box_url = "http://cloud-images.ubuntu.com/vagrant/precise/current/precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-vagrant-disk1.box"
  config.vm.network :forwarded_port, guest: 8000, host: 8080
end
</code></pre>

<p>The URL <a href="http://cloud-images.ubuntu.com/vagrant/precise/current/precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-vagrant-disk1.box">http://cloud-images.ubuntu.com/vagrant/precise/current/precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-vagrant-disk1.box</a> is a boxed <a href="http://cloud-images.ubuntu.com/vagrant/precise/current/precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-vagrant-disk1.box">Ubuntu 12.04 amd64 (for VirtualBox)</a> that I found in <a href="http://www.vagantbox.es">vagrantbox.es</a>.</p>

<p>Once the file is edited and saved, if now I run <code>vagrant up</code>, as it is the first time I fire that VM up, it will fetch the .box file (around 400M big) and create the VM.</p>

<p>Per default, the virtualization <em>provider</em> is VirtualBox, but I&rsquo;ve seen boxes for VMWare and for Linux Containers (LXC).</p>

<h2>Testing the port redirect</h2>

<p>Typing <code>vagrant ssh</code> in the shell inside the <code>vagrant/</code> directory will establish an SSH session with the VM.</p>

<p>Once there you can type this to get netcat listening on port 8000 of the VM:</p>

<pre><code>$ nc -l 0.0.0.0 8000
</code></pre>

<p>In other terminal you can try to access the port 8080 of your computer (the host of the VM), like:</p>

<pre><code>$ curl http://127.0.0.1:8080
</code></pre>

<p>It should redirect the packets from 8080/tcp in the host to 8000/tcp in the VM, and you should be able to see the HTTP request in the terminal where netcat is running.</p>

<h2>Trying a network bridge instead of a port redirect</h2>

<p>If the VM will need to access a computer in the same network as the host (e.g. a database server), or the VM will be accessed by a computer different than the host (e.g. a <a href="http://code.google.com/p/selenium/wiki/Grid2">Selenium Grid</a>), you may find easier to install a network bridge better than redirect some ports.</p>

<p>With that purpose in mind, the Vagrantfile should be something like:</p>

<pre><code># Vagrantfile API/syntax version. Don't touch unless you know what you're doing!
VAGRANTFILE_API_VERSION = "2"

Vagrant.configure(VAGRANTFILE_API_VERSION) do |config|
  config.vm.box = "test1"
  config.vm.box_url = "http://cloud-images.ubuntu.com/vagrant/precise/current/precise-server-cloudimg-amd64-vagrant-disk1.box"
  config.vm.network :public_network
end
</code></pre>

<p>The new Vagrant configuration can be applied with <code>vagrant reload</code>. That command will stop (in a polite and slow way) and start again the VMs, asking this time the user in the command-line for which network interface will be the VM bridged to.</p>

<p>Once the VM is completelly booted, from a <code>vagrant ssh</code> session, the available interfaces can be checked:</p>

<pre><code>$ ifconfig -a | perl -ne 'print "$1\n" if m/^(\S+)/'
eth0
eth1
lo
$ ifconfig eth1 | grep inet\ addr
          inet addr:192.168.0.105  Bcast:192.168.0.255  Mask:255.255.255.0
</code></pre>

<p>So, my VM got the IP address 192.168.0.105. If I start a netcat in port 90/tcp with <code>sudo nc -l 0.0.0.0 90</code></p>

<p>Then, I should be able to connect to port 90/tcp of the VM from my laptop, with something like <code>telnet 192.168.0.105 90</code>.</p>

<p>Once you stop playing with Vagrant, you can stop the VM via <code>vagrant halt</code>.</p>

<p>References:</p>

<ul>
<li><p> <a href="http://www.jedi.be/blog/2011/03/28/using-vagrant-as-a-team/">Using Vagrant as a Team &ndash; Just Enough Developed Infrastructure</a></p></li>
<li><p> <a href="http://www.vagrantbox.es/">A list of base boxes for Vagrant</a></p></li>
<li><p> <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com/downloads.html">Vagrant Packages and Tarballs</a></p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
